Finding Aid for the Edward Gordon Craig Papers LSC.1006
UCLA Library Special Collections
Edward Gordon Craig papers
1883-1966
UCLA Library Special Collections
Craig, Edward Gordon
LSC.1006
10.5 linear feet (15 boxes, 16 oversize boxes, and 3 cartons)
Edward Henry Gordon Craig (1872-1966) was a member of the Lyceum, London, where he received training as an actor and began his career in stage design and production (1889-95). He was appointed Royal Designer for Industry of the Royal College of Art (1938), made a Companion of Honour (1958) and was appointed president of the Mermaid Theatre, London (1964). The collection consists of materials related to Craig's career as an English stage designer and producer.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
B.F. Stevens & Brown, Limited, purchase, 1960.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 999645573606533
Biography
Edward Henry Gordon Craig was born in Stevenage, Hertfordshire, England, January 16, 1872; son of Ellen Terry, a Shakespearean actress, and Edward William Godwin, and brother of Edith Craig, a theatrical producer and director; attended Southfield Park School in Tunbridge Wells, Bradfield College, and Heidelberg College in Germany; married and later divorced from actress May Gibson; member of the Lyceum, London, where he received training as an actor and began his career in stage design and production, 1889-95; involved in productions such as Acis and Galatea (1902), The Vikings at Helgeland (1903), and Much Ado About Nothing (1903); publications include: The Art of the Theatre (1905), On the Art of Theatre (1911), Scene (1923), Woodcuts and Some Words (1924) and a partial biography titled, Index to the Story of My Days (1957); magazine publications include: The Page (1898-1901) and The Mask (1908-29); appointed Royal Designer for Industry of the Royal College of Art, 1938; made a Companion of Honour, 1958; president of the Mermaid Theatre, London (1964); died July 29, 1966 in Vence, France.
Chronology
Missing Title
January 16, 1872 Edward Henry Gordon Craig born at Stevenage, Hertsfordshire, England. Son of Ellen Terry and Edward William Godwin.
1883-1886 Southfield Park School, Tunbridge Wells
1884-1885 Visits United States on tour with Ellen Terry and Henry Irving. Makes first speaking appearance on stage in Eugene Aram.
1886-1887 Bradfield College.
1887-1888 Heidelberg College, Heidelberg.
1888-1889 Southfield Park School, Tunbridge Wells, as a private student.
1889-1892 At the Lyceum, London, under the direction of Henry Irving; provincial tours.
1893 At the Lyceum. Met James Pryde and William Nicholson (the Beggarstaff artists) and began wood carving; at Uxbridge does his first stage production, de Musset's On ne badine pas avec l'amour.
1894 Provincial tours.
1895 Leaves the Lyceum; provincial tours.
1896 Romeo and Juliet and Hamlet
1897 Meets Martin Shaw, the English composer and conductor.
1898 The Page
1899 Gordon Craig's Book of Penny Toys
1900 Bookplates, a booklet. Presents Dido and Aeneas
1901 Dido and Aeneas and The Masque of Love
1902 Acis and Galatea and The Masque of Love in London. Publishes souvenir program illustrated by his woodcuts for the performance. Designs settings for Bethlehem
1903 The Harvest Home. Designs sets for Fred Terry's production of Sword and Song and enters theatrical management with Ellen Terry and Edith Craig (Edward Gordon Craig's sister) in production of Ibsen's The Vikings and Much Ado about Nothing
1904 Venice Preserved
1905 The Art of the Theatre
1906 Isadora Duncan - Six Movement Designs in Germany. Meets Eleonora Duse in Berlin and designs sets for Rosmersholm
1907 The White Fan
1908 The Mask in Florence as forum for theatre criticism; publishes A Portfolio of Etchings. Travels to Moscow to discuss Stanislavsky's production of Hamlet
1910 Travels to Moscow.
1911 On the Art of the Theatre. W.B. Yeats uses Craig's new screens in sets for his plays at the Abbey Theatre, Dublin. Honored by dinner in London on July 16. In Moscow for the presentation of Hamlet
1913 A Living Theatre
1914-1916 School closes due to war and lack of funds; suspends publication of The Mask, writes marionette plays.
1917 Moves to the Villa Raggio, Rapallo, Italy.
1918 The Mask in April. Publishes The Marionette
1919 The Mask. The Theatre Advancing
1922 Invited to open the International Exhibition of Theatre Art and Craft at the Stedelijk Museum, Amsterdam. Exhibit travels to London and Manchester.
1923 Scene
1924 Woodcuts and Some Words, and Nothing, or the Bookplate
1925 Books and Theatres
1926 The Crown Pretenders
1930 Hamlet with Craig's prints is published. In A Production-1926, Craig's illustrations for The Crown Pretenders are published. Also published the biography, Henry Irving
1931 Ellen Terry and her Secret Self
1934 Invited to Volta Conference in Rome by Pirandello and Marconi; meets Marinetti, Maeterlinck, and Gropius.
1935 Visits Moscow and meets Brecht, Litvanov and Eisenstein.
1938 Appointed a Royal Designer for Industry.
1940 Taken to Stalag 142, Besançon, as a British citizen living in occupied Paris.
1957 Index to the Story of my Days
1958 Made a Companion of Honour.
1962 Eight Wood Engravings for Hamlet
1966 Dies in Vence, France.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of materials related to Craig's career as an English stage designer and producer. Includes correspondence, manuscripts, books owned and annotated by Craig, articles by or referring to Craig, photographs, designs, and ephemera.
Related Material
Rudolph Holzapfel Collection of Edward Gordon Craig Material (Collection 1482). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Online Item Available
Portions of this collection have been digitized and are available online: Edward G. Craig Papers (1 item).
List of Added Entries
Bernhardt, Sarah, 1844-1923.
Craig, Edith, 1869-1947.
Craig, Edward Anthony, 1904-.
The crown pretenders.
de Walden, Lord Howard.
Greet, Sir Ben, 1857-1936.
Housman, Laurence, 1865-1959.
Irving, Sir Henry, 1838-1905.
St. John, Christopher Marie (pseudonym).
Terry, Dame Ellen, 1847-1928.
Shaw, Martin Fallas, 1875-1958.
List of Added Entries
1. Actor G92, E86.
2. Stage Manager G86, E82.
3. Ophelia.
4. Ophelia Mad G136, E124.
5. Bird Dancer.
6. Ghost with Crown G17, E17.
7. Ghost with Bone G115, E110.
8. Hamlet & Daemon (Large).
9. Hamlet & Daemon (Small) G77, E70.
10. Hamlet with Skull G154, E150.
11. Laertes G160, E156.
12. Queen G134, E123.
13. A Lord (Guildenstern) G170, E162.
14. Seated Figure (Large).
14C. Seated Figure (Small).
15. King Claudius G122, E114.
16. Actor (3/4 length)--two blocks: second E64.
17. Polonius G24, E24.
18. Osric G168, E160.
19. Yorick G155, E151.
20. Gravediggers.
21. Candlebearer 1.
22. Candlebearer 2.
23. Candlebearer 3.
24. Candlebearer 4.
25. Doubt G162, E74.
26. Soldiers seated G10, E10.
27. Ghost in flames G11, E11.
28. Courtier.
29. Courtier.
30. Hamlet with curtain G21, E21.
31. Hamlet/Horatio profile.
32. Mask for Queen.
33. Soldier with Shield (Large) G9, E9.
34. Soldier with Shield (Small) G140.
Block 2 E128.
35. Fencer A:. Block 1, Block 2, Block 3 G175, E167.
36. Fencer B:. Block 1, Block 2 G175, E167, Block 3.
37. Hamlet & King Claudius G109, E102.
38. S.1 & S.3 Black Girl.
39. Girl with Stick.
40. Shylock.
41. Antonio.
42. Bassanio.
43. Lorenzo.
44. Lawyer.
45. Young Gobbo.
46. Old Gobbo.
47. Lady in Waiting.
48. Three Witches.
49. Running Figure.
50. The Jewess.
51. Cuchulain.
52. Priestess.
53. Group of Four Men.
54. Mask.
55. Mask.
56. Rosencrantz.
57. Guildenstern.
58. Iphigenia.
59. Mourners.
60. The Jew.
61B. Beauty.
62. The Beast.
63. Group of Eight Men.
64. Moses.
65. Lust.
66. Dancing Girl.
67. Hunger.
68. Girl with Ball.
69. Susanna.
70. First Elder.
71. Second Elder.
72. Hecuba.
73. Ophelia with Willow.
74. Roman Actor.
75. Electra.
76. Roman Actor.
77. Roman Actor.
78A. Roman Actor, Block 1.
78B. Roman Actor, Block 2.
79. The Scrivener.
80. The Priest.
81. Worshipper.
82. Gravedigger (Second) G149, E144.
82B. Gravedigger (First) G150, E146.
83. Portia.
84. Fear.
85. Eve.
86. Kultur, Culture, Cultura et cie.
87. Self-Portrait.
88. Thespis.
89. Hamlet with Sword:. Block 1, Block 2 G111, E105.
90. Shakespeare.
Set designers -- England -- Archives.; Theatrical producers and directors -- England -- Archives.; Craig, Edward Gordon, 1872-1966
- Section One: Manuscripts
  - Original Manuscripts
    - Scheme for the formation of The Order of the Mask. n.p., circa 1906.; (1 item, 25 cm. in diameter) (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents note
      Circular piece of wood with pencilled notations by Craig.
    - A note upon Scene to the editor of The London Times. Rapallo, Italy, October 7, 1907.; (5 leaves, typescript) (Box 1, Folder 2)
      With holograph corrections.
    - Art and the Nation. n.p., circa 1910.; (8 leaves, holograph) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Necessities [Florence], circa 1910.; (3 leaves, holograph) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - The Painter in the Theatre. Florence, circa 1910.; (4 leaves, holograph) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Socialism-- Syndicalism--Realism. Florence, circa 1910.; (1 leaf, holograph) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Stage scenery. n.p., circa 1910.; (13 leaves. Typescript. Signed on first page) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Stage scenery article. n.p., circa 1910.; (15 leaves. Typescript and holograph. Illustrated with pen and ink sketches. Initialled) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - The Theatre: A Note of Warning. Paris, circa 1910.; (4 leaves, holograph) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - A True Story. n.p., circa 1910.; (8 leaves, holograph, signed) (Box 1, Folder 10)
      In Craig's hand: A true story. 8pp. manuscript to William Gamble, USA.
    - Hamlet. n.p., circa 1913.; (2 leaves, holograph) (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Rough draft of critical note for Towards a New Theatre, London, Dent.
    - The Third Illumination. n.p., 1913.; (4 leaves. Typescript) (Box 1, Folder 12)
      With holograph corrections by Craig.
    - Mr. Fish and Mrs. Bones; a Motion in Seven Scenes by Orlando Furioso [pseudonym] Italy, 1916.; (2 p.l., 11 leaves) (Box 1, Folder 13)
      First typescript copy. In wrapper lettered and dated by Craig.
    - Rome, L.M. A Man of the Theatre: Gordon Craig., August 18, 1918.; (4 leaves. Typescript carbon) (Box 1, Folder 14)
      With holograph annotations by Craig.
      Published in Il Tempo, Rome.
    - Speech on scene development delivered before the Workers' Guild. n.p., June 18, 1920.; (11 leaves. Typescript) (Box 1, Folder 15)
      With holograph corrections. Initialed and dated by Craig.
    - [Fragments]. n.p., n.d.; (7 items) (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Published Material with Manuscript Additions
    - Improvements in stage scenery. Provisional specification. Completed specification. no.1771. Approved by King's Patent Agency, Limited. London: His Majesty's Stationery Office, 1910.; (3pp.) (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Patent with Craig's invention of a series of double-jointed folding screens for producing scenic effects on stage.
      Also, 2 folding pages of illustration.
      With this: Correspondence to Craig from King's Patent Agency, Limited, pertaining to Appeal against refusal of Russian patent. London, 1912 (3 items).
    - On the Art of the Theatre. London: William Heinemann, Limited, 1924.; (xxii, 296pp.) (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Presentation copy to Teddy from the author, 1924, with some corrections and notes by E.A. Craig.
      Bound in, Rules. School for the art of the theatre. Florence, 1913 (12 leaves).
      Noted, the first signed. Tipped-in on paste-down endpaper is photo of Edward Gordon Craig, dated 1926.
  - Proof Copies and Duplicates of Published Items
    General note
    Catalogued in the Rare Books Catalog, Department of Special Collections.
    - Die Kunst des Theaters. Ubersetztundeingeleitet von Maurice Magnus mit einem vorwort von Harry Graf Kessler. Berlin: H. Seeman, 1905.; (40pp. Paper wrapper. Fragile. Duplicate) (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Translation of Craig's The Art of the Theatre, London: Foulis.
    - De kunst van het theater. Vertaling van Donaert van M.A.J. Bauer. Amsterdam: S.L. van Looy, 1906.; (48pp. Paper wrapper. Fragile. Duplicate) (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Translation of Craig's The Art of the Theatre, London: Foulis, 1905.
    - [On] The Art of the Theatre. London, 1911.; (252pp., Unbound) (Box 1, Folder 21)
      Proof copy.
    - [On] The Art of the Theatre by Edward Gordon Craig. London: Heinemann, 1911.; (250pp., bound, signed on title page) (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Second proof copy with holograph corrections.
      Presentation copy to Elena [Mrs. Gordon] Craig.
    - Towards a New Theatre; Forty Designs for Stage Scenes With Critical Notes by the Inventor, Edward Gordon Craig. London: J.M. Dent & Sons, Limited, 1912.; OVERSIZE ITEM A; (90 leaves of which 7 leaves are printed) (Box 26)
      Dummy copy of first edition.
    - Towards a New Theatre; Forty Designs for Stage Scenes With Critical Notes by the Inventor, Edward Gordon Craig. London: J.M. Dent & Sons, Limited, 1913.; OVERSIZE ITEM B; (90 leaves. Unbound) (Box 26)
      Proof copy with holograph corrections by the author.
    - Towards a New Theatre. Screens, January 21, 1913.; (1 leaf) (Folder 2)
      First proof sheet for p.35 of Towards a New Theatre. Edinburgh: Ballantine Press. Holograph corrections by the author.
    - Scene; by E. Gordon Craig, with a foreward and an introductory poem by John Masefield. London: Oxford University Press, 1923.; (xii, 30pp. Number 39 of 1000. Signed) (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Nothing; or the Bookplate by Edward Gordon Craig with a handlist by Edward Carrick. London: Chatto and Windus, 1924.; (x, 28pp. Number 271 of 280 printed. Signed) (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Henry Irving. London, J.M. Dent & Sons, Limited, 1930.; (xii, 252pp.) (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Dust jacket and advertising material bound in. Inscribed to Teddy and Nell... P.
  - Privately Printed and Bound Manuscripts
    - Plans for the production of The Merchant of Venice. London, 1910.; (2 p.l., 15 leaves. Bound folio) (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Directions for set design and lighting with holograph explanatory notes by Gordon Craig for Ellen Terry. Signed and dated by Ellen Terry on flyleaf.
    - First arrangement with the printed blocks invented by Gordon Craig in 1912 - Paris. Florence, 1914.; (2 p.l., 65 leaves. Bound folio in wooden box. Privately printed in a limited edition of two) (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Hand pulls from woodcuts by Craig of arrangements for Hamlet. Initialed and dated by Craig with holograph notes on flyleaf and on individual prints.
  - Prompt Books
    - Shakespeare, William. Much Ado About Nothing; a comedy in five acts. Arranged for the stage by Henry Irving and presented at the Lyceum Theatre on Wednesday, October 11, 1882. London: Chiswick Press, 1887.; (74 leaves, in paper covers. Fragile) (Box 3, Folder 1)
      With holograph annotations by Ellen Terry (in pencil) and Gordon Craig (in pen).
    - The Works of William Shakespeare edited by Henry Irving and Frank A. Marshall. London: Blackie & Son, 1888-1889. (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - vol.1: Annotated by Craig with sketches and tipped in holograph notes, circa 1888.; item 2; (430pp.) (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - vol.4: Signed on title page Gordon Craig Berlin., - 1888 -.; item 3; (422pp.) (Box 3, Folder 1)
        Text with holograph annotations.
      - vol.6: Inscribed on title page Gordon Craig from Henry Irving., October 13, 1889.; item 4; (430pp.) (Box 3, Folder 1)
        With holograph annotations by Craig about the illustrations of Gordon Browne and the plays.
    - Katherine and Petruchio; a comedy in three acts altered by David Garrick from The Taming of the Shrew by William Shakespeare. French. London, 1892 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      Rebound and interleaved with Craig's sketches and notes for stage production.
      Inscribed on flyleaf by Craig, Lyceum Theatre, London [1892].
    - Browning, Robert. A Blot on the Scutcheon. n.p., 1892-1893. (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Rebound with Gordon Craig embossed in gold on cover.
      Copious holograph notes and stage directions interleaved with text of play.
      Signed and noted, studied in 1892-1893.
    - de Musset, Alfred. No Trifling With Love. n.p., December 1893. (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Rebound and interleaved with Craig's holograph notes for the production.
      Signed and dated by Gordon Craig, March, 1893.
    - Browning, Robert. Fra Lippo Lippi. n.p., 1894.; (3 p.l., 22 leaves) (Box 4, Folder 4)
      Rebound and interleaved with Craig's holograph notes and stage arrangements.
      Signed and dated by Craig.
    - Shakespeare, William. A Midsummer Night's Dream. n.p., 1896.; (9 leaves) (Box 4, Folder 5)
      Holograph notes and sketches for Scene One, Act Two written on pages from a printed text of the play [London, 1896].
    - Stevenson, Robert L. and William Henley. Macaire. n.p., 1896. (Box 4, Folder 6)
      Rebound and interleaved with Craig's notes and sketches.
      Signed on front cover and flyleaf.
      With this: Selby, Charles, Robert Macaire and John Dicks. Dicks' Standard Plays (no.325). London, n.d. Pamphlet, 16pp.
    - Shakespeare, William. Macbeth. The Chiswick Shakespeare. London: Bell, 1902. 1899.; (xi, 111pp.) (Box 4, Folder 7)
      Inscribed in ink on front flyleaf by Craig with his sketches throughout.
  - Production Notes
    - Production notes and sketches of set designs for Othello, The Crown Pretenders, and others. n.p., (7 items) (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Notebooks and Sketchbooks
    - Sketchbook. v.p., 1896-1906.; (39 leaves, pen and ink wash and chalk sketches. Cover is hand-colored by Craig) (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Includes designs for Hamlet, Romeo and Juliet, Peer Gynt, Lady from the Sea, and Caesar and Cleopatra.
      With notes and dates by Craig for each sketch.
    - Notebook. n.p., 1897.; (100 leaves. 8 leaves. contain holograph notes in pencil and pen. Signed and dated on cover) (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Used during Craig's production of Dido and Aeneas.
    - Sketchbook. n.p., 1898-1900.; OVERSIZE ITEM C; (32 leaves, 6 sketches mounted to 5 leaves) (Box 26)
      Ink and wash drawings for Gordon Craig's Book of Penny Toys.
    - Sketchbook. v.p., 1903-1904.; (135 leaves) (Box 5, Folder 3)
      Holograph notes and sketches for Venice Preserved, Salome, Bethlehem, and Hamlet.
      Initialed and dated.
    - Sketchbook. v.p., 1906.; OVERSIZE ITEM D; (69 leaves, large cardboard-covered book with loose pages) (Box 26)
      Production notes and sketches for Rosmersholm; Caesar and Cleopatra; the Moscow production of Hamlet; the Berlin-Dresden tour with Isadora Duncan; the School of the Theatre; and a holograph draft of an 11pp. article on materials to be used in the theatre of the future.
      Titled, dated and initialed by Craig on cover, Stockholm Book - Berlin-1906 - EGC.
      3 pages missing January 1995 L' Europe A Place of Beautiful Things W. Nicholson [?]
      Replaced with photocopies from microfilm. Original fragile--use photocopy only.
    - Writing album. v.p., 1906-1907.; (17 leaves, holograph) (Box 5, Folder 4)
      Notations of profits and expenses on the Isadora Duncan tour of Germany and Holland.
    - Notebook on movement. v.p., 1907-1920.; (73 leaves, holograph) (Box 5, Folder 5)
      notes and sketches indicating development towards Scene.
      Sketch and cover notes by Craig.
    - Minute Book of the Society of the Theatre. London, 1912-1913.; (60 leaves, typescript and holograph) (Box 5, Folder 6)
      The Society of the Theatre was formed by Craig in 1912 to found a school for the art of the theatre. Committee members included Craig, Haldane MacFall, Lovat Fraser, William Butler Yeats, Ernest Marriott and Ezra Pound.
- Section Two: Books Owned and Annotated by Craig
  - Pyle, Howard. The Merry Adventures of Robin Hood. New York: Scribner's, 1884. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Inscribed To Edward Gordon Craig from Henry Irving... January 1885 - on the eve of his first appearance on any stage - may angels bless and guard him. Chicago.
  - Shakespeare, William. Macbeth. London: Cattermole and Partridge, 1888.; (18 leaves) (Box 6, Folder 2)
    Souvenir of Macbeth produced at the Lyceum Theatre, December 29, 1888.
    Every illustration annotated by Craig with sketches and criticism.
  - Verne, Jules. Dick Sands, the Boy Captain. London: Low, Marsden, Searle and Rivington, 1879.; (486pp.) (Box 6, Folder 3)
    Inscribed on front paste down endpaper For Bobby from Father Ted. A splendid book. I read it in the year 1884 - it was jolly exciting.
    On front free endpaper, Edward Wardell - Southfield Park School - Southborough, Tunbridge Wells - April 26, 1884 and Gordon Craig-1906.
- Section Three: Periodicals Edited by Craig
  (Duplicates of items catalogued in Rare Books Catalog)
  - The Mask; a Monthly Leaflet of the Art of the Theatre (vol.8 no.1-3 and 8). Florence, 1918.; (4 items) (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - The Marionette Tonight (May 24) at 12:30 (vol.1 no.1-3, 10-12). Florence, 1918.; (6 items) (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Section Four: Published Articles and Reprints with Contributions by or Reference to Craig
  - [Two woodcuts by Gordon Craig]. The dome; an Illustrated Magazine and Review of Literature, Music, Architecture and the Graphic Arts (vol.2, no.6). New Series. London, March 1899. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Much Ado About Nothing - Footlights in Particular; a Talk With Mr. Gordon Craig. by B. The Tatler (no.98). London, May 13, 1903.; (Clipped article) (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - The Harvest Home, with colored woodcut by Gordon Craig. The Green Sheaf (no.3). London, 1903. (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - The Theatre: Trade or Art? by Gordon Craig. The Morning Post. London, December 26, 1903.; (Clipped article) (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Deutsche Kunst und Dekoration (vol.16 no.10). Berlin, July 1905. (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Osborn, Max. Edward Gordon Craig - Berlin., (pp.587-595) (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Craig, Gordon. Etwas über den regisseur und die bühnen-ausstattung., (pp.596-604) (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Craig, Gordon. Neue steinzeug-gefässe., (p.605) (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Bredt, E.W. Moderne bauten analten strassen., (pp.606-615) (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Which Era? by J.S. [pseudonym] Reprinted from The Mask (vol.4, no.4). Florence, 1912.; (1 leaf) (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - The Russian Ballet by J.S. [pseudonym] Reprinted from The Mask (vol.5 no.3). Florence, 1913.; (1 leaf) (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Mr. Gordon Craig's Theatre. A letter from Gordon Craig reprinted from The Nation (vol.14). Florence, October 4, 1913.; (2 leaves) (Box 6, Folder 13)
    With holograph notes by Craig.
  - Mr. Gordon Craig's Theatre. A letter from N.D. Laurence reprinted from The Nation (vol.14). Florence, November 1, 1913.; (1 leaf) (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - The Music Hall and the Church. A letter by Gordon Craig reprinted from The Mask. Florence, January 1914.; (4 leaves) (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - The Theatre and the New Civilization. By Gordon Craig. Theatre Arts Magazine (vol.3, no.1), January 1919; (3 leaves, clipped article) (Box 6, Folder 16)
    Heavily annotated by Gordon Craig and Ellen Terry.
  - Books, Mules and Idleness in Italy With Some Reflections on the Literature of the Theatre, part one. By Gordon Craig. The Bookman's Journal and Print Collector., September 17, 1920.; (2 leaves, clipped article) (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Am I Hostile to Literature? A Positive No. By Gordon Craig. The Graphic., August 18, 1923.; (1 leaf, clipped article) (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Review of The Crown Pretenders, Royal Theatre, Copenhagen. Theatre Arts Monthly (vol.11 no.4)., April 1927.; (1 leaf, photocopy) (Box 6, Folder 19)